<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: announcements | Aaron Klotz's Software Blog]]></title>
  <link href="https://dblohm7.ca/blog/categories/announcements/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://dblohm7.ca/"/>
  <updated>2022-05-06T17:40:31-06:00</updated>
  <id>https://dblohm7.ca/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Aaron Klotz]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[All Good Things...]]></title>
    <link href="https://dblohm7.ca/blog/2021/08/13/all-good-things/"/>
    <updated>2021-08-13T14:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>https://dblohm7.ca/blog/2021/08/13/all-good-things</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today is my final day as an employee of Mozilla Corporation.</p>

<p>My first patch landed in Firefox 19, and my final patch as an employee has
landed in Nightly for Firefox 93.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ll be moving on to something new in a few weeks&#8217; time, but for now, I&rsquo;d just
like to say this:</p>

<p>My time at Mozilla has made me into a better software developer, a better
leader, and more importantly, a better person.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;d like to thank all the Mozillians whom I have interacted with over the years
for their contributions to making that happen.</p>

<p>I will continue to update this blog with catch-up posts describing my Mozilla
work, though I am unsure what content I will be able to contribute beyond that.
Time will tell!</p>

<p>Until next time&hellip;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Coming Around Full Circle]]></title>
    <link href="https://dblohm7.ca/blog/2019/09/30/coming-around-full-circle/"/>
    <updated>2019-09-30T10:30:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>https://dblohm7.ca/blog/2019/09/30/coming-around-full-circle</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One thing about me that most Mozillians don&rsquo;t know is that, when I first applied to work at MoCo,
I had applied to work on the mobile platform. When all was said and done, it was decided at the time
that I would be a better fit for an opening on Taras Glek&rsquo;s platform performance team.</p>

<p>My first day at Mozilla was October 15, 2012 &mdash; I will be celebrating my seventh anniversary at MoCo in
just a couple short weeks! Some people with similar tenures have suggested to me that we are now
&ldquo;old guard,&rdquo; but I&rsquo;m not sure that I feel that way! Anyway, I digress.</p>

<p>The platform performance team eventually evolved into a desktop-focused performance team by late 2013.
By the end of 2015 I had decided that it was time for a change, and by March 2016 I had moved over to
work for Jim Mathies, focusing on Gecko integration with Windows. I ended up spending the next twenty
or so months helping the accessibility team port their Windows implementation over to multiprocess.</p>

<p>Once Firefox Quantum 57 hit the streets, I scoped out and provided technical leadership for the
InjectEject project, whose objective was to tackle some of the root problems with DLL injection that
were causing us grief in Windows-land.</p>

<p>I am proud to say that, over the past three years on Jim&rsquo;s team, I have done the best work of my career.
I&rsquo;d like to thank Brad Lassey (now at Google) for his willingness to bring me over to his group, as well as
Jim, and David Bolter (a11y manager at the time) for their confidence in me. As somebody who had spent most
of his adult life having no confidence in his work whatsoever, their willingness to entrust me with
taking on those risks and responsibilities made an enormous difference in my self esteem and my
professional life.</p>

<p>Over the course of H1 2019, I began to feel restless again. I knew it was time for another change. What
I did not expect was that the agent of that change would be James Willcox, aka Snorp. In Whistler, Snorp
planted the seed in my head that I might want to come over to work with him on GeckoView, within the
mobile group which David was now managing.</p>

<p>The timing seemed perfect, so I made the decision to move to GeckoView. I had to finish tying up some
loose ends with InjectEject, so all the various stakeholders agreed that I&rsquo;d move over at the end of Q3 2019.</p>

<p>Which brings me to this week, when I officially join the GeckoView team, working for Emily Toop. I find
it somewhat amusing that I am now joining the team that evolved from the team that I had originally applied
for back in 2012. I have truly come full circle in my career at Mozilla!</p>

<p>So, what&rsquo;s next?</p>

<ul>
<li><p>I have a couple of InjectEject bugs that are pretty much finished, but just need some polish and
code reviews before landing.</p></li>
<li><p>For the next month or two at least, I am going to continue to meet weekly with Jim to assist with
the transition as he ramps up new staff on the project.</p></li>
<li><p>I still plan to be the module owner for the Firefox Launcher Process and the MSCOM library, however most
day-to-day work will be done by others going forward;</p></li>
<li><p>I will continue to serve as the mozglue peer in charge of the DLL blocklist and DLL interceptor, with
the same caveat.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>Switching over to Android from Windows does not mean that I am leaving my Windows experience at the door; I
would like to continue to be a resource on that front, so I would encourage people to continue to ask me
for advice.</p>

<p>On the other hand, I am very much looking forward to stepping back into the mobile space. My first crack at
mobile was as an intern back in 2003, when I was working with some code that had to run on PalmOS 3.0! I have not
touched Android since I shipped a couple of utility apps back in 2011, so I am looking forward to learning
more about what has changed. I am also looking forward to learning more about native development on Android,
which is something that I never really had a chance to try.</p>

<p>As they used to say on Monty Python&rsquo;s Flying Circus, &ldquo;And now for something completely different!&rdquo;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
