<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: mozilla | Aaron Klotz at Mozilla]]></title>
  <link href="http://dblohm7.ca/blog/categories/mozilla/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://dblohm7.ca/"/>
  <updated>2017-04-07T15:02:54-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://dblohm7.ca/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Aaron Klotz]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Asynchronous Plugin Initialization: Requiem]]></title>
    <link href="http://dblohm7.ca/blog/2017/04/07/asynchronous-plugin-initialization-requiem/"/>
    <updated>2017-04-07T15:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://dblohm7.ca/blog/2017/04/07/asynchronous-plugin-initialization-requiem</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>My colleague bsmedberg is going to be removing asynchronous plugin
initialization in <a title="Remove support for async plugin init" href="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=1352575">bug 1352575</a>. Sadly the feature never became solid enough
to remain enabled on release, so we cut our losses and cancelled the project
early in 2016. Now that code is just a bunch of dead weight. With the
deprecation of non-Flash NPAPI plugins in Firefox 52, our developers are now
working on simplifying the remaining NPAPI code as much as possible.</p>

<p>Obviously the removal of that code does not prevent me from discussing some of
the more interesting facets of that work.</p>

<p>Today I am going to talk about how async plugin init worked when web content
attempted to access a property on a plugin&rsquo;s scriptable object, when that
plugin had not yet completed its asynchronous initialization.</p>

<p>As <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Plugins/Guide/Scripting_plugins">described on MDN</a>,
the DOM queries a plugin for scriptability by calling <code>NPP_GetValue</code> with the
<code>NPPVpluginScriptableNPObject</code> constant. With async plugin init, we did not
return the true scriptable object back to the browser. Instead, we returned
a surrogate object. This meant that we did not need to synchronously wait for
the plugin to initialize before returning a scriptable object to the DOM.</p>

<p>If the DOM subsequently called into the surrogate object, the surrogate would
be forced to synchronize with the plugin. After all, the NPAPI itself is
entirely synchronous. I could only do so much fakery until eventually I had
to force the browser to synchronize with the plugin. While you may look at that
design and wonder whether it actually bought us anything, performance profiles
that I took at the time did indeed demonstrate that the asynchronous surrogate
scripting object did buy us enough additional concurrency to make the change
worthwhile.</p>

<p>Once the surrogate object had synchronized with the plugin, it would then mostly
act as a pass-through to the plugin&rsquo;s true scriptable object, with one notable
exception: property accesses.</p>

<p>The reason for this is not necessarily obvious, so allow me to explain:</p>

<p>The DOM usually sets up a scriptable object as follows:</p>

<pre><samp>
this.__proto__.__proto__.__proto__
</samp></pre>


<ul>
<li>Where <code>this</code> is the WebIDL object (ie, content&rsquo;s <code>&amp;lt;embed&amp;gt;</code> element);</li>
<li>Whose prototype is the NPAPI scriptable object;</li>
<li>Whose prototype is the shared WebIDL prototype;</li>
<li>Whose prototype is <code>Object.prototype</code>.</li>
</ul>


<p>NPAPI is reentrant (some might say <em>insanely</em> reentrant). It is possible (and
indeed common) for a plugin to set properties on the WebIDL object from within
the plugin&rsquo;s <code>NPP_New</code>.</p>

<p>Suppose that the DOM tries to access a property on the plugin&rsquo;s WebIDL object
that is normally set by the plugin&rsquo;s <code>NPP_New</code>. In the asynchronous case, the
plugin&rsquo;s initialization might still be in progress, so that property might not
yet exist.</p>

<p>In the case where the property does not yet exist on the WebIDL object, JavaScript
then moves onto the first prototype, which would actually be the async surrogate.
The async surrogate now synchronizes with the plugin. At this point the plugin is
guaranteed to have finished its initialization.</p>

<p>Now we have a problem: JS is already examining the NPAPI scriptable object,
however the plugin has completed initializing and set its properties (including
the one that we&rsquo;re interested in) on the WebIDL object. JS is already looking too
far up the prototype chain!</p>

<p>The surrogate needed to be aware of this when it synchronized with the plugin
during a property access. If the plugin had already completed its initialization
(rendering synchronization unnecessary), the surrogate would simply pass the
property access on to the real NPAPI scriptable object. On the other hand, if a
synchronization was performed, the surrogate would retry the WebIDL object by
querying for the WebIDL object&rsquo;s &ldquo;own&rdquo; properties, and return the own property
if it now existed.</p>

<p>If I hadn&rsquo;t made the asynchronous surrogate scriptable object do that, we would
have ended up with a strange situation where the DOM&rsquo;s initial property access
on an embed could fail non-deterministically.</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s enough chatter for today. I enjoy blogging about my crazy hacks that make
the impossible, umm&hellip; possible, so maybe I&rsquo;ll write some more of these in the
future.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[On WebExtensions]]></title>
    <link href="http://dblohm7.ca/blog/2015/08/30/on-webextensions/"/>
    <updated>2015-08-30T02:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://dblohm7.ca/blog/2015/08/30/on-webextensions</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There has been enough that has been said over the past week about <a href="https://blog.mozilla.org/addons/2015/08/21/the-future-of-developing-firefox-add-ons/">WebExtensions</a>
that I wasn&rsquo;t sure if I wanted to write this post. As usual, I can&rsquo;t seem to
help myself. Note the usual disclaimer that this is my personal opinion. Further
note that I have no involvement with WebExtensions at this time, so I write this
from the point of view of an observer.</p>

<h2>API? What API?</h2>

<p>I shall begin with the proposition that the legacy, non-jetpack
environment for addons is not an API. As ridiculous as some readers might
consider this to be, please humour me for a moment.</p>

<p>Let us go back to the acronym, &ldquo;API.&rdquo; <strong>A</strong>pplication <strong>P</strong>rogramming <strong>I</strong>nterface.
While the usage of the term &ldquo;API&rdquo; seems to have expanded over the years to encompass
just about any type of interface whatsoever, I&rsquo;d like to explore the first letter of that
acronym: <em>Application</em>.</p>

<p>An <em>Application</em> Programming Interface is a specific type of interface that is
exposed for the purposes of building applications. It typically provides a
formal abstraction layer that isolates applications from the implementation
details behind the lower tier(s) in the software stack. In the case of web
browsers, I suggest that there are two distinct types of applications:
web content, and extensions.</p>

<p>There is obviously a very well defined API for web content. On the other hand,
I would argue that Gecko&rsquo;s legacy addon environment is not an API at all! From
the point of view of an extension, there is no abstraction, limited formality,
and not necessarily an intention to be used by applications.</p>

<p>An extension is imported into Firefox with full privileges and can access whatever
it wants. Does it have access to interfaces? Yes, but are those interfaces intended
for <em>applications</em>? Some are, but many are not. The environment that Gecko
currently provides for legacy addons is analagous to an operating system running
every single application in kernel mode. Is that powerful? Absolutely! Is that
the best thing to do for maintainability and robustness? Absolutely not!</p>

<p>Somewhere a line needs to be drawn to demarcate this abstraction layer and
improve Gecko developers&#8217; ability to make improvements under the hood. Last
week&rsquo;s announcement was an invitation to addon developers to help shape that
future. Please participate and please do so constructively!</p>

<h2>WebExtensions are not Chrome Extensions</h2>

<p>When I first heard rumors about WebExtensions in Whistler, my source made it
very clear to me that the WebExtensions initiative is not about making Chrome
extensions run in Firefox. In fact, I am quite disappointed with some of the
press coverage that seems to completely miss this point.</p>

<p>Yes, WebExtensions will be implementing some APIs to be <em>source compatible</em>
with Chrome. That makes it easier to port a Chrome extension, but porting will
still be necessary. I like the Venn Diagram concept that the <a href="https://wiki.mozilla.org/WebExtensions/FAQ">WebExtensions FAQ</a>
uses: Some Chrome APIs will not be available in WebExtensions. On the other hand,
WebExtensions will be providing APIs above and beyond the Chrome API set that
will maintain Firefox&rsquo;s legacy of extensibility.</p>

<p>Please try not to think of this project as Mozilla taking functionality away.
In general I think it is safe to think of this as an opportunity to move that
same functionality to a mechanism that is more formal and abstract.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Win32 APIs]]></title>
    <link href="http://dblohm7.ca/blog/2015/07/28/interesting-win32-apis/"/>
    <updated>2015-07-28T11:30:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://dblohm7.ca/blog/2015/07/28/interesting-win32-apis</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Yesterday I decided to diff the export tables of some core Win32 DLLs to see what&rsquo;s
changed between Windows 8.1 and the Windows 10 technical preview. There weren&rsquo;t
many changes, but the ones that were there are quite exciting IMHO. While
researching these new APIs, I also stumbled across some others that were
added during the Windows 8 timeframe that we should be considering as well.</p>

<h2>Volatile Ranges</h2>

<p>While my diff showed these APIs as new exports for Windows 10, the MSDN docs
claim that these APIs are actually new for the Windows 8.1 Update. Using the
<a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/windows/desktop/dn781436%28v=vs.85%29.aspx"><code>OfferVirtualMemory</code></a>
and <a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/windows/desktop/dn781437%28v=vs.85%29.aspx"><code>ReclaimVirtualMemory</code></a>
functions, we can now specify ranges of virtual memory that are safe to
discarded under memory pressure. Later on, should we request that access be
restored to that memory, the kernel will either return that virtual memory to us
unmodified, or advise us that the associated pages have been discarded.</p>

<p>A couple of years ago we had an intern on the Perf Team who was working on
bringing this capability to Linux. I am pleasantly surprised that this is now
offered on Windows.</p>

<h2><code>madvise(MADV_WILLNEED)</code> for Win32</h2>

<p>For the longest time we have been hacking around the absence of a <code>madvise</code>-like
API on Win32. On Linux we will do a <code>madvise(MADV_WILLNEED)</code> on memory-mapped
files when we want the kernel to read ahead. On Win32, we were opening the
backing file and then doing a series of sequential reads through the file to
force the kernel to cache the file data. As of Windows 8, we can now call
<a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/windows/desktop/hh780543%28v=vs.85%29.aspx"><code>PrefetchVirtualMemory</code></a>
for a similar effect.</p>

<h2>Operation Recorder: An API for SuperFetch</h2>

<p>The <a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/hh437562%28v=vs.85%29.aspx"><code>OperationStart</code></a>
and <a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/hh437558%28v=vs.85%29.aspx"><code>OperationEnd</code></a>
APIs are intended to record access patterns during a file I/O operation.
SuperFetch will then create prefetch files for the operation, enabling prefetch
capabilities above and beyond the use case of initial process startup.</p>

<h2>Memory Pressure Notifications</h2>

<p>This API is not actually new, but I couldn&rsquo;t find any invocations of it in the
Mozilla codebase. <a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/windows/desktop/aa366541%28v=vs.85%29.aspx"><code>CreateMemoryResourceNotification</code></a>
allocates a kernel handle that becomes signalled when physical memory is running
low. Gecko already has facilities for handling memory pressure events on other
platforms, so we should probably add this to the Win32 port.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[WaitMessage Considered Harmful]]></title>
    <link href="http://dblohm7.ca/blog/2015/03/12/waitmessage-considered-harmful/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-12T15:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://dblohm7.ca/blog/2015/03/12/waitmessage-considered-harmful</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I could apologize for the clickbaity title, but I won&rsquo;t. I have no shame.</p>

<p>Today I want to talk about some code that we imported from Chromium some time
ago. I replaced it in Mozilla&rsquo;s codebase a few months back in <a title="IPC message pump for windows should use WinUtils::WaitForMessage" href="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=1072752">bug 1072752</a>:</p>

<p><figure class='code'><figcaption><span> (message_pump_win.cc)</span> <a href='/downloads/code/message_pump_win.cc'>download</a></figcaption>
<div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>261</span>
<span class='line-number'>262</span>
<span class='line-number'>263</span>
<span class='line-number'>264</span>
<span class='line-number'>265</span>
<span class='line-number'>266</span>
<span class='line-number'>267</span>
<span class='line-number'>268</span>
<span class='line-number'>269</span>
<span class='line-number'>270</span>
<span class='line-number'>271</span>
<span class='line-number'>272</span>
<span class='line-number'>273</span>
<span class='line-number'>274</span>
<span class='line-number'>275</span>
<span class='line-number'>276</span>
<span class='line-number'>277</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='c++'><span class='line'>    <span class="c1">// A WM_* message is available.</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="c1">// If a parent child relationship exists between windows across threads</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="c1">// then their thread inputs are implicitly attached.</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="c1">// This causes the MsgWaitForMultipleObjectsEx API to return indicating</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="c1">// that messages are ready for processing (Specifically, mouse messages</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="c1">// intended for the child window may appear if the child window has</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="c1">// capture).</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="c1">// The subsequent PeekMessages call may fail to return any messages thus</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="c1">// causing us to enter a tight loop at times.</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="c1">// The WaitMessage call below is a workaround to give the child window</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="c1">// some time to process its input messages.</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="n">MSG</span> <span class="n">msg</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="p">{</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">};</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="n">DWORD</span> <span class="n">queue_status</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">GetQueueStatus</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">QS_MOUSE</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="k">if</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="n">HIWORD</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">queue_status</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">&amp;</span> <span class="n">QS_MOUSE</span> <span class="o">&amp;&amp;</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="o">!</span><span class="n">PeekMessage</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="o">&amp;</span><span class="n">msg</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nb">NULL</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">WM_MOUSEFIRST</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">WM_MOUSELAST</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">PM_NOREMOVE</span><span class="p">))</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="n">WaitMessage</span><span class="p">();</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="p">}</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure></p>

<p>This code is wrong. <strong>Very</strong> wrong.</p>

<p>Let us start with the calls to <code>GetQueueStatus</code> and <code>PeekMessage</code>. Those APIs
mark any messages already in the thread&rsquo;s message queue as having been seen,
such that they are no longer considered &ldquo;new.&rdquo; Even though those function calls
do not remove messages from the queue, any messages that were in the queue at
this point are considered to be &ldquo;old.&rdquo;</p>

<p>The logic in this code snippet is essentially saying, &ldquo;if the queue contains
mouse messages that do not belong to this thread, then they must belong to an
attached thread.&rdquo; The code then calls <code>WaitMessage</code> in an effort to give the
other thread(s) a chance to process their mouse messages. This is where the code
goes off the rails.</p>

<p>The <a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/windows/desktop/ms644956%28v=vs.85%29.aspx">documentation</a>
for <code>WaitMessage</code> states the following:</p>

<blockquote><p>Note that <code>WaitMessage</code> does not return if there is unread input in the message
queue after the thread has called a function to check the queue. This is
because functions such as <code>PeekMessage</code>, <code>GetMessage</code>, <code>GetQueueStatus</code>,
<code>WaitMessage</code>, <code>MsgWaitForMultipleObjects</code>, and <code>MsgWaitForMultipleObjectsEx</code>
check the queue and then change the state information for the queue so that
the input is no longer considered new. A subsequent call to <code>WaitMessage</code> will
not return until new input of the specified type arrives. The existing unread
input (received prior to the last time the thread checked the queue) is ignored.</p></blockquote>

<p><code>WaitMessage</code> will only return if there is <em>a new</em> (as opposed to <em>any</em>) message
in the queue for the calling thread. Any messages for the calling thread that
were already in there at the time of the <code>GetQueueStatus</code> and <code>PeekMessage</code> calls
are no longer new, so they are ignored.</p>

<p>There might very well be a message at the head of that queue that should be
processed by the current thread. Instead it is ignored while we wait for other
threads. Here is the crux of the problem: we&rsquo;re waiting on other threads whose
input queues are attached to our own! That other thread can&rsquo;t process its
messages because our thread has messages in front of its messages; on the other
hand, our thread has blocked itself!</p>

<p>The only way to break this deadlock is for new messages to be added to the queue.
That is a big reason why we&rsquo;re seeing things like <a title="Page doesn't load/render if the mouse is not moving" href="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=1105386">bug 1105386</a>: Moving the
mouse adds new messages to the queue, making <code>WaitMessage</code> unblock.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve already eliminated this code in Mozilla&rsquo;s codebase, but the challenge is
going to be getting rid of this code in third-party binaries that attach their
own windows to Firefox&rsquo;s windows.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Attached Input Queues on Firefox for Windows]]></title>
    <link href="http://dblohm7.ca/blog/2015/03/03/attached-input-queues-on-firefox-for-windows/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-03T17:28:06-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://dblohm7.ca/blog/2015/03/03/attached-input-queues-on-firefox-for-windows</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve <a href="http://dblohm7.ca/blog/2012/11/22/plugin-hang-user-interface-for-firefox/">previously</a> <a href="http://dblohm7.ca/blog/2013/02/15/plugin-hang-ui-on-aurora/">blogged</a>
indirectly about attached input queues, but today I want to address the issue directly. What once was a nuisance in the realm of plugin hangs has grown into a more
serious problem in the land of OMTC and e10s.</p>

<p>As a brief recap for those who are not very familiar with this problem: imagine two windows, each on their own separate threads, forming a parent-child relationship
with each other. When this situation arises, Windows implicitly attaches together and synchronizes their input queues, putting each thread at the mercy of the other
attached threads&#8217; ability to pump messages. If one thread does something bad in its message pump, any other threads that are attached to it are likely to be affected as well.</p>

<p>One of the biggest annoyances when it comes to knowledge about which threads are affected, is that we are essentially flying blind. There is no
way to query Windows for information about attached input queues. This is unfortunate, as it would be really nice to obtain some specific knowledge to allow us to
analyze the state of Firefox threads&#8217; input queues so that we can mitigate the problem.</p>

<p>I had previously been working on a personal side project to make this possible, but in light of recent developments (and a <a href="https://twitter.com/nsIAnswers/status/565883284748795905">tweet from bsmedberg</a>),
I decided to bring this investigation under the umbrella of my full-time job. I&rsquo;m pleased to announce that I&rsquo;ve finished the first cut of a utility that I call
the Input Queue Visualizer, or <code>iqvis</code>.</p>

<p><code>iqvis</code> consists of two components, one of which is a kernel-mode driver. This driver exposes input queue attachment data to user mode. The <code>iqvis</code> user-mode
executable is the client that queries the driver and outputs the results. In the next section I&rsquo;m going to discuss the inner workings of <code>iqvis</code>. Following that, I&rsquo;ll
discuss the <a href="#results">results</a> of running <code>iqvis</code> on an instance of Firefox.</p>

<h2><a name="internals"></a>Input Queue Visualizer Internals</h2>

<p>First of all, let&rsquo;s start off with this caveat: <strong>Nearly everything that this driver does involves undocumented APIs and data structures</strong>. Because of this, <code>iqvis</code>
does some things that you should never do in production software.</p>

<p>One of the big consequences of using undocumented information is that <code>iqvis</code> requires pointers to very specific locations
in kernel memory to accomplish things. These pointers will change every time that Windows is updated. To mitigate this, I kind of cheated: it turns out that
debugging symbols exist for all of the locations that <code>iqvis</code> needs to access! I wrote the <code>iqvis</code> client to invoke the <code>dbghelp</code> engine to extract the pointers that
I need from Windows symbols and send those values as the input to the <code>DeviceIoControl</code> call that triggers the data collection. Passing pointers from user mode to be
accessed in kernel mode is a very dangerous thing to do (and again, I would never do it in production software), but it is damn convenient for <code>iqvis</code>!</p>

<p>Another issue is that these undocumented details change between Windows versions. The initial version of <code>iqvis</code> works on 64-bit Windows 8.1, but different code is required
for other major releases, such as Windows 7. The <code>iqvis</code> driver theoretically will work on Windows 7 but I need to make a few bug fixes for that case.</p>

<p>So, getting those details out of the way, we can address the crux of the problem: we need to query input queue attachment information from <code>win32k.sys</code>, which is the
driver that implements USER and GDI system calls on Windows NT systems.</p>

<p>In particular, the window manager maintains a linked list that describes thread attachment info as a triple that points to the &ldquo;from&rdquo; thread, the &ldquo;to&rdquo; thread, and a count.
The count is necessary because the same two threads may be attached to each other multiple times. The <code>iqvis</code> driver walks this linked list in a thread-safe way to obtain
the attachment data, and then copies it to the output buffer for the <code>DeviceIoControl</code> request.</p>

<p>Since <code>iqvis</code> involves a device driver, and since I have not digitally signed that device driver, one can&rsquo;t just run <code>iqvis</code> and call it a day. This program won&rsquo;t work
unless the computer was either booted with kernel debugging enabled, or it was booted with driver signing temporarily disabled.</p>

<h2><a name="results"></a>Running <code>iqvis</code> against Firefox</h2>

<p>Today I ran <code>iqvis</code> using today&rsquo;s Nightly 39 as well as the lastest release of Flash. I also tried it with Flash Protected Mode both disabled and enabled.
(Note that these examples used an older version of <code>iqvis</code> that outputs thread IDs in hexadecimal. The current version uses decimal for its output.)</p>

<h3>Protected Mode Disabled</h3>

<pre><samp>FromTID ToTID Count
ac8 df4 1
</samp></pre>


<p>Looking up the thread IDs:</p>

<ul>
<li><code>df4</code> is the Firefox main thread;</li>
<li><code>ac8</code> is the plugin-container main thread.</li>
</ul>


<p>I think that the output from this case is pretty much what I was expecting to see. The protected mode case, however, is more interesting.</p>

<h3>Protected Mode Enabled</h3>

<pre><samp>FromTID ToTID Count
f8c dbc 1
794 f8c 3
</samp></pre>


<p>Looking up the thread IDs:</p>

<ul>
<li><code>dbc</code> is the Firefox main thread;</li>
<li><code>f8c</code> is the plugin-container main thread;</li>
<li><code>794</code> is the Flash sandbox main thread.</li>
</ul>


<p>Notice how Flash is attached to plugin-container, which is then attached to Firefox. Notice that transitively the Flash sandbox is effectively attached to Firefox,
confirming previous hypotheses that I&rsquo;ve discussed with colleagues in the past.</p>

<p>Also notice how the Flash sandbox attachment to plugin-container has a count of 3!</p>

<h2>In Conclusion</h2>

<p>In my opinion, my Input Queue Visualizer has already yielded some very interesting data. Hopefully this will help us to troubleshoot our issues in the future. Oh,
and the code is up on <a href="https://github.com/dblohm7/iqvis">GitHub</a>! It&rsquo;s poorly documented at the moment, but just remember to only try running it on 64-bit Windows
8.1 for the time being!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
