<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: win32 | Aaron Klotz at Mozilla]]></title>
  <link href="http://dblohm7.ca/blog/categories/win32/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://dblohm7.ca/"/>
  <updated>2021-02-26T12:07:42-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://dblohm7.ca/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Aaron Klotz]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Win32 Gotchas]]></title>
    <link href="http://dblohm7.ca/blog/2017/07/17/win32-gotchas/"/>
    <updated>2017-07-17T12:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://dblohm7.ca/blog/2017/07/17/win32-gotchas</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For the second time since I have been at Mozilla I have encountered a situation
where hooks are called for notifications of a newly created window, but that
window has not yet been initialized properly, causing the hooks to behave badly.</p>

<p>The first time was inside our window neutering code in IPC, while the second
time was in our accessibility code.</p>

<p>Every time I have seen this, there is code that follows this pattern:</p>

<pre><code class="c++">HWND hwnd = CreateWindowEx(/* ... */);
if (hwnd) {
  // Do some follow-up initialization to hwnd (Using SetProp as an example):
  SetProp(hwnd, "Foo", bar);
}
</code></pre>

<p>This seems innocuous enough, right?</p>

<p>The problem is that <code>CreateWindowEx</code> calls hooks. If those hooks then try to do
something like <code>GetProp(hwnd, "Foo")</code>, that call is going to fail because the
&ldquo;Foo&rdquo; prop has not yet been set.</p>

<p>The key takeaway from this is that, if you are creating a new window, you must
do any follow-up initialization from within your window proc&rsquo;s <code>WM_CREATE</code>
handler. This will guarantee that your window&rsquo;s initialization will have
completed before any hooks are called.</p>

<p>You might be thinking, &ldquo;But I don&rsquo;t set any hooks!&rdquo; While this may be true, you
must not forget about hooks set by third-party code.</p>

<p>&ldquo;But those hooks won&rsquo;t know anything about my program&rsquo;s internals, right?&rdquo;</p>

<p>Perhaps, perhaps not. But when those hooks fire, they give third-party software
the opportunity to run. In some cases, those hooks might even cause the thread
to <em>reenter your own code</em>. Your window had better be completely initialized
when this happens!</p>

<p>In the case of my latest discovery of this issue in <a title="Window emulation needs to SetProp inside WM_CREATE" href="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=1380471">bug 1380471</a>, I made it
possible to use a C++11 lambda to simplify this pattern.</p>

<p><a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/windows/desktop/ms632680.aspx"><code>CreateWindowEx</code></a>
accepts a <code>lpParam</code> parameter which is then passed to the <code>WM_CREATE</code> handler
as the <code>lpCreateParams</code> member of a <a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/windows/desktop/ms632603.aspx"><code>CREATESTRUCT</code></a>.</p>

<p>By setting <code>lpParam</code> to a pointer to a <code>std::function&lt;void(HWND)&gt;</code>, we may then
supply any callable that we wish for follow-up window initialization.</p>

<p>Using the previous code sample as a baseline, this allows me to revise the code
to safely set a property like this:</p>

<pre><code class="c++">std::function&lt;void(HWND)&gt; onCreate([](HWND aHwnd) -&gt; void {
  SetProp(aHwnd, "Foo", bar);
});

HWND hwnd = CreateWindowEx(/* ... */, &amp;onCreate);
// At this point is already too late to further initialize hwnd!
</code></pre>

<p>Note that since <code>lpParam</code> is always passed during <code>WM_CREATE</code>, which always fires
before <code>CreateWindowEx</code> returns, it is safe for <code>onCreate</code> to live on the stack.</p>

<p>I liked this solution for the a11y case because it preserved the locality of
the initialization code within the function that called <code>CreateWindowEx</code>; the
window proc for this window is implemented in another source file and the
follow-up initialization depends on the context surrounding the <code>CreateWindowEx</code>
call.</p>

<p>Speaking of window procs, here is how that window&rsquo;s <code>WM_CREATE</code> handler invokes
the callable:</p>

<pre><code class="c++">switch (uMsg) {
  case WM_CREATE: {
    auto createStruct = reinterpret_cast&lt;CREATESTRUCT*&gt;(lParam);
    auto createProc = reinterpret_cast&lt;std::function&lt;void(HWND)&gt;*&gt;(
      createStruct-&gt;lpCreateParams);

    if (createProc &amp;&amp; *createProc) {
      (*createProc)(hwnd);
    }

    return 0;
  }
  // ...
</code></pre>

<p><strong>TL;DR:</strong> If you see a pattern where further initialization work is being done
on an <code>HWND</code> after a <code>CreateWindowEx</code> call, move that initialization code to your
window&rsquo;s <code>WM_CREATE</code> handler instead.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why I prefer using CRITICAL_SECTIONs for mutexes in Windows Nightly builds]]></title>
    <link href="http://dblohm7.ca/blog/2017/06/12/why-i-prefer-using-critical-sections-for-mutexes-in-windows-nightly-builds/"/>
    <updated>2017-06-12T15:50:43-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://dblohm7.ca/blog/2017/06/12/why-i-prefer-using-critical-sections-for-mutexes-in-windows-nightly-builds</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In the past I have argued that our Nightly builds, both debug and release, should
use <code>CRITICAL_SECTION</code>s (with full debug info) for our implementation of
<code>mozilla::Mutex</code>. I&rsquo;d like to illustrate some reasons why this is so useful.</p>

<h2>They enable more utility in WinDbg extensions</h2>

<p>Every time you initialize a <code>CRITICAL_SECTION</code>, Windows inserts the CS&rsquo;s
debug info into a process-wide linked list. This enables their discovery by
the Windows debugging engine, and makes the <code>!cs</code>, <code>!critsec</code>, and <code>!locks</code>
commands more useful.</p>

<h2>They enable profiling of their initialization and acquisition</h2>

<p>When the &ldquo;Create user mode stack trace database&rdquo; gflag is enabled, Windows
records the call stack of the thread that called <code>InitializeCriticalSection</code>
on that CS. Windows also records the call stack of the owning thread once
it has acquired the CS. This can be very useful for debugging deadlocks.</p>

<h2>They track their contention counts</h2>

<p>Since every CS has been placed in a process-wide linked list, we may now ask
the debugger to dump statistics about every live CS in the process. In
particular, we can ask the debugger to output the contention counts for each
CS in the process. After running a workload against Nightly, we may then take
the contention output, sort it descendingly, and be able to determine which
<code>CRITICAL_SECTION</code>s are the most contended in the process.</p>

<p>We may then want to more closely inspect the hottest CSes to determine whether
there is anything that we can do to reduce contention and all of the extra
context switching that entails.</p>

<h2>In Summary</h2>

<p>When we use <code>SRWLOCK</code>s or initialize our <code>CRITICAL_SECTION</code>s with the
<code>CRITICAL_SECTION_NO_DEBUG_INFO</code> flag, we are denying ourselves access to this
information. That&rsquo;s fine on release builds, but on Nightly I think it is worth
having around. While I realize that most Mozilla developers have not used this
until now (otherwise I would not be writing this blog post), this rich debugger
info is one of those things that you do not miss until you do not have it.</p>

<p>For further reading about critical section debug info, check out
<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150419055323/https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/magazine/cc164040.aspx">this</a>
archived article from MSDN Magazine.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[New Team, New Project]]></title>
    <link href="http://dblohm7.ca/blog/2016/04/06/new-team-new-project/"/>
    <updated>2016-04-06T21:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://dblohm7.ca/blog/2016/04/06/new-team-new-project</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In February of this year I switched teams: After 3+ years on Mozilla&rsquo;s
Performance Team, and after having the word &ldquo;performance&rdquo; in my job description
in some form or another for several years prior to that, I decided that it was
time for me to move on to new challenges. Fortunately the Platform org was
willing to have me set up shop under the (e10s|sandboxing|platform integration)
umbrella.</p>

<p>I am pretty excited about this new role!</p>

<p>My first project is to sort out the accessibility situation under Windows e10s.
This started back at Mozlando last December. A number of engineers from across
the Platform org, plus me, got together to brainstorm. Not too long after we had
all returned home, I ended up making a suggestion on an email thread that has
evolved into the core concept that I am currently attempting. As is typical at
Mozilla, no deed goes unpunished, so I have been asked to flesh out my ideas.
An overview of this plan is available on the <a href="https://wiki.mozilla.org/Electrolysis/Accessibility/Windows">wiki</a>.</p>

<p>My hope is that I&rsquo;ll be able to deliver a working, &ldquo;version 0.9&rdquo; type of demo
in time for our London all-hands at the end of Q2. Hopefully we will be able to
deliver on that!</p>

<h2>Some Additional Notes</h2>

<p>I am using this section of the blog post to make some additional notes. I don&rsquo;t
feel that these ideas are strong enough to commit to a wiki yet, but I do want
them to be publicly available.</p>

<p>Once concern that our colleagues at NVAccess have identified is that the
current COM interfaces are too chatty; this is a major reason why screen
readers frequently inject libraries into the Firefox address space. If we serve
our content a11y objects as remote COM objects, there is concern that performance
would suffer. This concern is not due to latency, but rather due to frequency
of calls; one function call does not provide sufficient information to the a11y
client. As a result, multiple round trips are required to fetch all of the
information that is required for a particular DOM node.</p>

<p>My gut feeling about this is that this is probably a legitimate concern, however
we cannot make good decisions without quantifying the performance. My plan going
forward is to proceed with a na&iuml;ve implementation of COM remoting to start,
followed by work on reducing round trips as necessary.</p>

<h2>Smart Proxies</h2>

<p>One idea that was discussed is the idea of the content process speculatively
sending information to the chrome process that might be needed in the future.
For example, if we have an <code>IAccessible</code>, we can expect that multiple properties
will be queried off that interface. A smart proxy could ship that data across
the RPC channel during marshaling so that querying that additional information
does not require additional round trips.</p>

<p>COM makes this possible using &ldquo;handler marshaling.&rdquo; I have dug up some
information about how to do this and am posting it here for posterity:</p>

<p><a href="https://www.microsoft.com/msj/0599/com/com0599.aspx">House of COM, May 1999 <em>Microsoft Systems Journal</em></a>;<br/>
<a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/windows/desktop/ms683786.aspx">Implementing and Activating a Handler with Extra Data Supplied by Server</a> on MSDN;<br/>
Wicked Code, August 2000 <em>MSDN Magazine</em>. This is not available on the MSDN Magazine website but I have an archived copy on CD-ROM.<br/></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[New mozdbgext command: !iat]]></title>
    <link href="http://dblohm7.ca/blog/2016/02/11/new-mozdbgext-command-iat/"/>
    <updated>2016-02-11T18:30:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://dblohm7.ca/blog/2016/02/11/new-mozdbgext-command-iat</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As of today I have added a new command to <code>mozdbgext</code>: <code>!iat</code>.</p>

<p>The syntax is pretty simple:</p>

<p><code>!iat &lt;hexadecimal address&gt;</code></p>

<p>This address shouldn&rsquo;t be just any pointer; it should be the address of an
entry in the current module&rsquo;s import address table (IAT). These addresses
are typically very identifiable by the <code>_imp_</code> prefix in their symbol names.</p>

<p>The purpose of this extension is to look up the name of the DLL from whom the
function is being imported. Furthermore, the extension checks the expected
target address of the import with the actual target address of the import. This
allows us to detect API hooking via IAT patching.</p>

<h3>An Example Session</h3>

<p>I fired up a local copy of Nightly, attached a debugger to it, and dumped the
call stack of its main thread:</p>

<pre><samp>
 # ChildEBP RetAddr
00 0018ecd0 765aa32a ntdll!NtWaitForMultipleObjects+0xc
01 0018ee64 761ec47b KERNELBASE!WaitForMultipleObjectsEx+0x10a
02 0018eecc 1406905a USER32!MsgWaitForMultipleObjectsEx+0x17b
03 0018ef18 1408e2c8 xul!mozilla::widget::WinUtils::WaitForMessage+0x5a
04 0018ef84 13fdae56 xul!nsAppShell::ProcessNextNativeEvent+0x188
05 0018ef9c 13fe3778 xul!nsBaseAppShell::DoProcessNextNativeEvent+0x36
06 0018efbc 10329001 xul!nsBaseAppShell::OnProcessNextEvent+0x158
07 0018f0e0 1038e612 xul!nsThread::ProcessNextEvent+0x401
08 0018f0fc 1095de03 xul!NS_ProcessNextEvent+0x62
09 0018f130 108e493d xul!mozilla::ipc::MessagePump::Run+0x273
0a 0018f154 108e48b2 xul!MessageLoop::RunInternal+0x4d
0b 0018f18c 108e448d xul!MessageLoop::RunHandler+0x82
0c 0018f1ac 13fe78f0 xul!MessageLoop::Run+0x1d
0d 0018f1b8 14090f07 xul!nsBaseAppShell::Run+0x50
0e 0018f1c8 1509823f xul!nsAppShell::Run+0x17
0f 0018f1e4 1514975a xul!nsAppStartup::Run+0x6f
10 0018f5e8 15146527 xul!XREMain::XRE_mainRun+0x146a
11 0018f650 1514c04a xul!XREMain::XRE_main+0x327
12 0018f768 00215c1e xul!XRE_main+0x3a
13 0018f940 00214dbd firefox!do_main+0x5ae
14 0018f9e4 0021662e firefox!NS_internal_main+0x18d
15 0018fa18 0021a269 firefox!wmain+0x12e
16 0018fa60 76e338f4 firefox!__tmainCRTStartup+0xfe
17 0018fa74 77d656c3 KERNEL32!BaseThreadInitThunk+0x24
18 0018fabc 77d6568e ntdll!__RtlUserThreadStart+0x2f
19 0018facc 00000000 ntdll!_RtlUserThreadStart+0x1b
</samp></pre>


<p>Let us examine the code at frame 3:</p>

<pre><samp>
14069042 6a04            push    4
14069044 68ff1d0000      push    1DFFh
14069049 8b5508          mov     edx,dword ptr [ebp+8]
1406904c 2b55f8          sub     edx,dword ptr [ebp-8]
1406904f 52              push    edx
14069050 6a00            push    0
14069052 6a00            push    0
14069054 ff159cc57d19    call    dword ptr [xul!_imp__MsgWaitForMultipleObjectsEx (197dc59c)]
1406905a 8945f4          mov     dword ptr [ebp-0Ch],eax
</samp></pre>


<p>Notice the function call to <code>MsgWaitForMultipleObjectsEx</code> occurs indirectly;
the call instruction is referencing a pointer within the <code>xul.dll</code> binary
itself. This is the IAT entry that corresponds to that function.</p>

<p>Now, if I load <code>mozdbgext</code>, I can take the address of that IAT entry and execute
the following command:</p>

<pre><samp>
0:000> !iat 0x197dc59c
Expected target: USER32.dll!MsgWaitForMultipleObjectsEx
Actual target: USER32!MsgWaitForMultipleObjectsEx+0x0
</samp></pre>


<p><code>!iat</code> has done two things for us:</p>

<ol>
<li>It did a reverse lookup to determine the module and function name for the
import that corresponds to that particular IAT entry; and</li>
<li>It followed the IAT pointer and determined the symbol at the target address.</li>
</ol>


<p>Normally we want both the expected and actual targets to match. If they don&rsquo;t,
we should investigate further, as this mismatch may indicate that the IAT has
been patched by a third party.</p>

<p>Note that <code>!iat</code> command is breakpad aware (provided that you&rsquo;ve already
loaded the symbols using <code>!bploadsyms</code>) but can fall back to the Microsoft
symbol engine as necessary.</p>

<p>Further note that the <code>!iat</code> command does not yet accept the <code>_imp_</code> symbolic
names for the IAT entries, you need to enter the hexadecimal representation of
the pointer.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Announcing mozdbgext]]></title>
    <link href="http://dblohm7.ca/blog/2016/01/26/announcing-mozdbgext/"/>
    <updated>2016-01-26T12:45:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://dblohm7.ca/blog/2016/01/26/announcing-mozdbgext</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A well-known problem at Mozilla is that, while most of our desktop users run
Windows, most of Mozilla&rsquo;s developers do not. There are a lot of problems that
result from that, but one of the most frustrating to me is that sometimes
those of us that actually use Windows for development find ourselves at a
disadvantage when it comes to tooling or other productivity enhancers.</p>

<p>In many ways this problem is also a Catch-22: People don&rsquo;t want to use Windows
for many reasons, but tooling is big part of the problem. OTOH, nobody is
motivated to improve the tooling situation if nobody is actually going to
use them.</p>

<p>A couple of weeks ago my frustrations with the situation boiled over when I
learned that our <code>Cpp</code> unit test suite could not log symbolicated call stacks,
resulting in my filing of <a title="cppunittests do not look up breakpad symbols for logged stack traces" href="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=1238305">bug 1238305</a> and <a title="Set _NT_SYMBOL_PATH on Windows test machines" href="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=1240605">bug 1240605</a>. Not only could we
not log those stacks, in many situations we could not view them in a debugger
either.</p>

<p>Due to the fact that PDB files consume a large amount of disk space, we don&rsquo;t
keep those when building from integration or try repositories. Unfortunately
they are be quite useful to have when there is a build failure. Most of our
integration builds, however, do include breakpad symbols. Developers may also
explicitly <a href="https://wiki.mozilla.org/ReleaseEngineering/TryServer#Getting_debug_symbols">request symbols</a>
for their try builds.</p>

<p>A couple of years ago I had begun working on a WinDbg debugger extension that
was tailored to Mozilla development. It had mostly bitrotted over time, but I
decided to resurrect it for a new purpose: to help WinDbg<sup><a href="#fn1" id="r1">*</a></sup>
grok breakpad.</p>

<h2>Enter mozdbgext</h2>

<p><a href="https://github.com/dblohm7/mozdbgext"><code>mozdbgext</code></a> is the result. This extension
adds a few commands that makes Win32 debugging with breakpad a little bit easier.</p>

<p>The original plan was that I wanted <code>mozdbgext</code> to load breakpad symbols and then
insert them into the debugger&rsquo;s symbol table via the <a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/windows/hardware/ff537943%28v=vs.85%29.aspx"><code>IDebugSymbols3::AddSyntheticSymbol</code></a>
API. Unfortunately the design of this API is not well equipped for bulk loading
of synthetic symbols: each individual symbol insertion causes the debugger to
re-sort its entire symbol table. Since <code>xul.dll</code>&rsquo;s quantity of symbols is in the
six-figure range, using this API to load that quantity of symbols is
prohibitively expensive. I tweeted a Microsoft PM who works on Debugging Tools
for Windows, asking if there would be any improvements there, but it sounds like
this is not going to be happening any time soon.</p>

<p>My original plan would have been ideal from a UX perspective: the breakpad
symbols would look just like any other symbols in the debugger and could be
accessed and manipulated using the same set of commands. Since synthetic symbols
would not work for me in this case, I went for &ldquo;Plan B:&rdquo; Extension commands that
are separate from, but analagous to, regular WinDbg commands.</p>

<p>I plan to continuously improve the commands that are available. Until I have a
proper README checked in, I&rsquo;ll introduce the commands here.</p>

<h3>Loading the Extension</h3>

<ol>
<li>Use the <code>.load</code> command: <code>.load &lt;path_to_mozdbgext_dll&gt;</code></li>
</ol>


<h3>Loading the Breakpad Symbols</h3>

<ol>
<li>Extract the breakpad symbols into a directory.</li>
<li>In the debugger, enter <code>!bploadsyms &lt;path_to_breakpad_symbol_directory&gt;</code></li>
<li>Note that this command will take some time to load all the relevant symbols.</li>
</ol>


<h3>Working with Breakpad Symbols</h3>

<p><strong>Note: You must have successfully run the <code>!bploadsyms</code> command first!</strong></p>

<p>As a general guide, I am attempting to name each breakpad command similarly to
the native WinDbg command, except that the command name is prefixed by <code>!bp</code>.</p>

<ul>
<li>Stack trace: <code>!bpk</code></li>
<li>Find nearest symbol to address: <code>!bpln &lt;address&gt;</code> where <em>address</em> is specified
as a hexadecimal value.</li>
</ul>


<h3>Downloading windbgext</h3>

<p>I have pre-built binaries (<a href="https://github.com/dblohm7/mozdbgext/blob/master/bin/32/mozdbgext.dll?raw=true">32-bit</a>, <a href="https://github.com/dblohm7/mozdbgext/blob/master/bin/64/mozdbgext.dll?raw=true">64-bit</a>) available for download.</p>

<p>Note that there are several other commands that are &ldquo;roughed-in&rdquo; at this point
and do not work correctly yet. Please stick to the documented commands at this
time.</p>

<hr />

<p><sup><a href="#r1" id="fn1">*</a></sup> When I write &ldquo;WinDbg&rdquo;, I am really
referring to any debugger in the <em>Debugging Tools for Windows</em> package,
including <code>cdb</code>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
